{
  "title": "General_Aptitude-_CSE - Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Verbal_Ability_–_CSE — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>The diagram below shows a river system consisting of 7 segments, marked P, Q, R, S, T, U, and V. It splits the land into 5 zones, marked Z1, Z2, Z3, Z4, and Z5. We need to connect these zones using the least number of bridges. Out of the following options, which one is correct? <br>Note: The figure shown is representative. <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q65_9c4479d6.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, and T</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, S, and T</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Bridges on Q, R, T, and V</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Bridges on P, Q, S, U, and V</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Bridges on Q, R, T, and V</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460441/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Based only on the conversation below, identify the logically correct inference:  <br><br>\n\"Even if I had known that you were in the hospital, I would not have gone there to see you\", Ramya told Josephine. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Ramya knew that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Ramya did not know that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Ramya and Josephine were once close friends; but now, they are not.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Josephine was in the hospital due to an injury to her leg.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>Ramya did not know that Josephine was in the hospital.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460445/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>The paper as shown in the figure is folded to make a cube where each square corresponds to a particular face of the cube. Which one of the following options correctly represents the cube?<br>Note: The figures shown are representative.  <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q59a_bbf0880b.webp\"><br><br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q59b_37c3fe6d.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>B</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>C</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>D</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460447/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>Bird : Nest :: Bee : __________   <br> Select the correct option to complete the analogy. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Kennel</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Hammock</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Hive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Lair</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>Hive</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460449/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Despite his initial hesitation, Rehman's __________ to contribute to the success of the project never wavered. <br>Select the most appropriate option to complete the above sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>ambivalence</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>satisfaction</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>resolve</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>revolve</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>resolve</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460450/gate-cse-2025-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>A square paper, shown in figure (I), is folded along the dotted lines as shown in the figures (II) and (III). Then a few cuts are made as shown in figure (IV). Which one of the following patterns will be obtained when the paper is unfolded?\n<br>Note: The figures shown are representative.<br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q64a_4c00fbae.webp\"><br><br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q64b_b423886b.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>B</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>C</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>D</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>A</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460092/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-9#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>\"I put the brown paper in my pocket along with the chalks, and possibly other things. I suppose everyone must have reflected how primeval and how poetical are the things that one carries in one's pocket: the pocket-knife, for instance the type of all human tools, the infant of the sword. Once I planned to write a book of poems entirely about the things in my pocket. But I found it would be too long: and the age of the great epics is past.\"  <br><br>\n(From G.K. Chesterton's \"A Piece of Chalk\")  <br><br>\nBased only on the information provided in the above passage, which one of the following statements is true? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The author of the passage carries a mirror in his pocket to reflect upon things.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The author of the passage had decided to write a poem on epics.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The pocket-knife is described as the infant of the sword.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Epics are described as too inconvenient to write.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The pocket-knife is described as the infant of the sword.</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460095/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>According to the map shown in the figure, which one of the following statements is correct?  <br>\nNote: The figure shown is representative. <br><img style=\"max-width:50%;height:auto;border-radius:8px;\" data-lazyloaded=\"1\" decoding=\"async\" src=\"images\\gatePYQ\\Verbal_Ability_–_CSE\\q60_d7b5bf82.webp\"><br> <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>The library is located to the northwest of the canteen.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>The hospital is located to the east of the chemistry lab.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>The classrooms and canteen are next to each other.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>The chemistry lab is to the southeast of the physics lab.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460096/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>Consider the relationships among P, Q, R, S, and T:  <br><br>\nP is the brother of Q.<br>\nS is the daughter of Q.<br>\nT is the sister of S. <br>\nR is the mother of Q.\n<br><br>\nThe following statements are made based on the relationships given above.<br><br>\nR is the grandmother of S.<br>\nP is the uncle of S and T.<br>\nR has only one son.<br>\nQ has only one daughter.\n<br><br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>Both (1) and (3) are true.</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>Only (3) is true.</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>Only (4) is true.</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>Both (1) and (2) are true.</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460097/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-4#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>The CEO's decision to downsize the workforce was considered myopic because it sacrificed long-term stability to accommodate short-term gains.  <br>\nSelect the most appropriate option that can replace the word \"myopic\" without changing the meaning of the sentence. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>visionary</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>progressive</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>innovative</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>shortsighted</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460099/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Ravi had _____________ younger brother who taught at _____________ university. He was widely regarded as _____________ honorable man.  <br>\nSelect the option with the correct sequence of articles to fill in the blanks. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>the; an; a</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>a; an; a</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>an; an; a</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>a; a; an</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460100/gate-cse-2025-set-1-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Sequence the following sentences in a coherent passage.<br><br>\nP:    This fortuitous geological event generated a colossal amount of energy and heat that resulted in the rocks rising to an average height of 4 km across the contact zone.\n<br>Q:    Thus, the geophysicists tend to think of the Himalayas as an active geological event rather than as a static geological feature.\n<br>R:    The natural  process  of  the  cooling  of  this massive  edifice  absorbed  large quantities of atmospheric carbon dioxide, altering the earth?s atmosphere and making it better suited for life.\n<br>S:    Many millennia ago, a breakaway chunk of bedrock from the Antarctic Plate collided with the massive Eurasian Plate. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>QPSR</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>QSPR</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>SRPQ</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>SPRQ</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422901/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>If '\\( \\rightarrow \\)' denotes increasing order of intensity, then the meaning of the words\n[walk \\( \\rightarrow \\) jog \\( \\rightarrow \\) sprint] is analogous to [bothered \\( \\rightarrow \\) ________ \\( \\rightarrow \\) daunted].<br>\nWhich one of the given options is appropriate to fill the blank? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>phased</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>phrased</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>fused</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>fazed</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422906/gate-cse-2024-set-2-ga-question-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>In the given text, the blanks are numbered (i)-(iv). Select the best match for all the\nblanks.  <br>\nSteve was advised to keep his head ___(i)___ before heading __(ii)__ to bat;\nfor, while he had a head __(iii)__ batting, he could only do so with a cool head\ns __(iv)__ his shoulders <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) down (iii) on (iv) for</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>(i) on (ii) down (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) out (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>(i) on (ii) out (iii) on (iv) for</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>(i) down (ii) out (iii) for (iv) on</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422781/gate-cse-2024-set-1-ga-6#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>If '\\( \\rightarrow \\)' denotes increasing order of intensity, then the meaning of the words\n[dry \\( \\rightarrow \\) arid \\( \\rightarrow \\) parched] is analogous to [diet \\( \\rightarrow \\) fast \\( \\rightarrow \\) _____].\n<br>\nWhich one of the given options is appropriate to fill the blank? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>starve</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>reject</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>feast</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>deny</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>starve</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422786/gate-cse-2024-set-1-ga-1#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}